Here we are back in the Colab, which has been running overnight for me and probably for you too, I
다시 콜랍입니다 밤새 틀어 놨는데 여러분도 그랬으면 좋겠네요
hope.
나처럼 당신도 열성적으로 매달렸잖아요
So this is showing the part in the colab where it's running away and you can see it's ticking through.
콜랍에 있는 이 부분이 흘러가는 걸 보여줍니다 돌아가는 게 보이죠?
It's more than halfway at this point as it makes its way through the four epochs.
지금까지는 네 개의 개혁을 거치며 절반 이상이 지났죠
Four epochs are not required for this.
네 개의 개혁은 필요 없어요
You only need to do one epoch, of course.
물론 한 개혁만 성공하면 돼요
And just that I'm a sucker for this stuff and loving it.
전 이런 걸 정말 좋아해요
So it's it's ticking away.
시간이 가고 있어요
Let's go to the fabulous weights and biases to see how it looks here.
멋진 무게와 바이어스로 가서 어떻게 보이는지 보죠
This is our run.
우리가 달려요
You remember in weights and biases.
무게와 편향성을 기억하죠
The navigation at the top here lets you see the different projects that you may have.
상단의 탐색은 여러분이 갖고 있는 다양한 프로젝트를 볼 수 있게 해줘요
And we're looking at my Pricer project, which is the one in question.
지금 보고 있는 건 문제의 프라이커 프로젝트예요
I've also got a Pricer GPT project for for where we fine tune GPT.
GPT를 미세 조정하기 위한 Pricer GPT 프로젝트도 있는데요
Um, and then here are the different runs I name the runs in the code after the date and time that they
여기 다양한 실행이 있어요 코드 내 실행에 이름을 붙였죠 실행이 시작된 날짜와 시간의
were kicked off.
이름을요
You don't need to do that.
그럴 필요 없어요
You can call them runs anything you want.
마음대로 불러도 돼요
I do this because it helps me be able to, uh, recollect when I did, what, run and so on.
달리기 같은 걸 할 때 기억이 잘 나거든요
So I found this quite a useful trick.
꽤 유용한 방법이었어요
But you could also name it to describe the kind of run that you're doing.
하지만 여러분이 작업하는 런을 설명하기 위해 이름을 붙일 수도 있어요
Um, and you can also rename it by, by right clicking on it.
오른쪽 클릭으로 이름을 다시 지을 수도 있어요
Uh, so the current run is this blue run right here.
현재는 이 블루 런이 있어요
This is what we've been running.
이게 우리가 해온 거예요
And if I zoom in on the training loss, which is the the diagram that really matters, you now know
훈련 손실을 확대해보면 이 도표가 정말 중요한데 여기서 보이는 게 교차 엔트로피
this is cross-entropy loss we're seeing here.
손실이란 걸 아시겠죠
Uh, and you'll see that it clearly has uh, this was the first epoch.
여길 보시면 확실히 첫 번째 시대예요
It comes down a bit here, uh, potentially because some overfitting starts to happen when it sees the
비트가 약간 내려갔는데 데이터를 두 번째로 볼 때 비트가 과잉 설정되기
data a second time, and then it drops again for the beginning of the third epoch here.
때문입니다 세 번째 이포크가 시작되면 다시 한 번 감소하죠
The thing that I'm not doing that is a very much a best practice that I should be doing is having a
제가 하지 않는 것은 최선의 관행으로 유효성 검사 데이터 집합을
validation data set, and we'd be able to see validation loss.
하는 것입니다 유효성 검사 손실을 볼 수 있죠
And I imagine what you'd find is that it maybe only decreases a little bit here, and maybe quite soon
보시면 아시겠지만 이 부분만 조금 줄어들고 머지않아 조금씩 늘어날
it will start to increase a bit because we are overfitting.
거예요 비트가 과하게 들어가니까요
Uh, we'll find that out by, by running the model in inference mode, but it would be better to see
추론 모드의 모델을 실행하면 알아낼 수 있지만 검증 결과를 보는
the validation results.
게 더 낫겠죠
And hopefully that's something that you are doing.
그게 당신이 하는 일이면 좋겠네요
And I would love to see those charts by the way.
그 차트 좀 보고 싶네요
So what we can also do is layer on top of this, the prior run that I had done when I ran it through
이 위에 레이어를 둘 수 있어요 완료까지 실행했을 때 실행했던
to completion.
거죠
Here we go.
시작할게요
Let's zoom in again on both of these runs together.
이 두 경기를 함께 확대해보죠
And what you'll see is that the two runs are very, very similar indeed.
보면 아시겠지만 두 번의 시도는 아주 비슷했어요
Obviously I had the same, um, the same hyperparameters, and I'd set random seeds.
물론 하이퍼파라미터도 같았고 무작위로 시드를 설정했어요
And so it's not not a great surprise, but it does show you that despite all of the complexity and everything
그리 놀랍진 않지만 모든 복잡한 상황에도 불구하고
that's going on, you do get the, the same numbers, um, from these runs.
get run에서 같은 숫자가 나온다는 걸 보여주죠
So that's somewhat comforting.
그래서 좀 위안이 돼요
Uh, and I think that's probably all to all to show you.
보여드릴 건 그게 다인 것 같네요
We can see that in terms of the learning rate that now, well, before we were suspicious that the blue
학습률 측면에서 보면 예전엔 의심을 안 했는데 지금은 파란
line, if we just look at the blue line only, uh, just for a moment, flashed up with what it used
선을 보면 잠깐이지만 예전에 보던 게 반짝거려요
to see.
보시면 알겠지만 마지막으로 찍은 건 이 정도 높이에서 찍었어요
And maybe you were skeptical about whether we were really seeing a nice, smooth curve.
매끄러운 곡선이 보이는지 회의적이었을 수도 있어요
And now you clearly see that it's coming down in a very nice way.
이제 아주 멋지게 무너지는 게 보이죠
So that cosine learning rate scheduler is a good trick to know, a good way to vary the learning rate
코사인 학습률 스케줄러는 알아두면 좋은 방법입니다 기간에 학습률을 다양하게 할
during the course of your batch.
수 있는 좋은 방법이죠
Okay.
네
And then final thing to show you is to flip to hugging face.
마지막으로 얼굴 껴안기 버튼을 눌러요
I'll mention if you look at this model, you'll see that the name of this ends in 11 seconds at that
이 모델을 보시면 이 이름의 끝이 11초 후에 타임스탬프로 끝나는 걸 보실 수
timestamp.
있어요
If we go over to Hugging Face in the hub, I've got all these different models.
허브에서 페이스 포옹으로 가면 다양한 모델이 있어요
And this one, this one ending in 11 seconds is, of course, the run in question that's running right
그리고 이 화면은 11초 안에 끝나는데, 물론 지금 실행중인 화면이죠
And in fact, it even says updated two hours ago.
2시간 전에 업데이트됐다고도 뜨네요
So we know it's the right one.
제대로 온 거예요
As I say, some people will just have the single repo they'll just write to for all of their different
어떤 사람들은 단일 압류만 갖기도 합니다 모든 실행에 대해 글로 작성하는 거죠 그게
runs, and that's a perfectly good way of doing it.
완벽하게 좋은 방법이에요
I prefer doing it this way, so I keep my my different runs completely separate.
전 이렇게 하는 게 좋아요 각각의 코스를 완전히 분리하는 거죠
And if I go into this repo we're now looking at if I click on files and versions, these are the files
이 압류로 가면 지금 보고 있는 건 파일과 버전을 클릭하면 이것과 관련된
associated with this.
파일들이죠
Run again the safe tensors.
안전한 텐서를 사용하세요
That's the business.
그게 사업이죠
That's where it all happens.
거기서 모든 게 시작되죠
It's 109MB worth of parameters that are the parameters of our Lora adapters.
109MB 정도의 파라미터가 로라 어댑터의 파라미터예요
Um, and over here you'll see history nine commits.
이쪽에는 역사 9가 커밋하는 걸 보실 수 있어요
If I click on this, it's showing me that just as I had asked in my parameters in my setup, uh, hugging
클릭을 하면, 설정에서 매개 변수에서 요청했던 것을 볼 수 있습니다 포옹하는 얼굴이 허브에
face has been saving this to the hub, uploading it, making a different revision of these model weights
저장되어 있고 업로드되어 있습니다 5,000 걸음마다 모델의 무게를 다르게
every 5000 steps.
수정하고 있네요
Um, and so, uh, that's something we'll have access to if we want to go back and do some, uh, do
그 액세스를 사용할 수 있습니다 과거로 돌아가 커밋에 대한 추론을
inference on any one of those different commits.
하고 싶다면요
And hopefully you can see why I like to keep it as a separate repo.
왜 따로 압류하는지 이해하셨으면 좋겠네요
So I don't muddle up the different saves during a particular run with the different versions of training.
그래서 여러 가지 세이브를 여러 가지 훈련과 혼동하지 않아요
Okay, I think that's enough of a tour of where we're at.
좋아요, 현장은 이 정도면 충분한 것 같아요
Uh, head back to the slides one more time before we actually get to inference.
추론으로 넘어가기 전에 슬라이드로 돌아가 주세요. Get it get get it.